Guide to the Saretta G. Hicks papers on Lady Deborah Moody ARC.276
Brooklyn Historical Society
Saretta G. Hicks papers on Lady Deborah Moody
circa 1960s
Brooklyn Historical Society
Hicks, Saretta G.
ARC.276
1.8 Linear Feet in two full manuscript boxes and two small boxes.
This collection consists of papers gathered and, in many cases, written by author Saretta G. Hicks during the period 1963 to 1965. The material includes her notes and research for an unfinished book about Lady Deborah Moody titled "Dangerous Woman: A Biography of Deborah, Lady Moody of Coney Island."
Conditions Governing Access
Open to users without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source and date of acquisition for accession 1978.170 are unknown. Accession 1980.003 was the gift of the estate of Saretta G. Hicks, 1980.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into four series by type. The subject files are arranged alphabetically.
Biographical note
Born circa 1583 in Avebury, England, Deborah Dunch "...was the daughter of a barrister, granddaughter of a Bishop, wife of a member of Parliament" and a distant relative to Oliver Cromwell by marriage. Her husband, Sir Henry Moody, was made a baronet by King James I in 1622. After her husband passed away in 1629, Lady Moody was beset with financial difficulties and, finding the political atmosphere in England increasingly insupportable, immigrated to Lynn, MA in 1639.
At first welcomed in Lynn, Lady Moody's sympathies for the Anabaptist movement soon created increasing difficulties for her. Writer Saretta G. Hicks's research points especially to Lady Moody's support of the Anabaptist practice of limiting baptism to adults as a major point of contention with members of the community. The Anabaptists, a minority in Massachusetts, also advocated a separation of church and state. Lady Moody left Massachusetts in 1643 in search of a more tolerant, or less controlling, atmosphere.
She settled in New Amsterdam (later New York City), but in 1645 led a group of English settlers to Long Island and established a colony at Gravesend, located at the southern tip of Long Island, an area somewhat sheltered from the Atlantic Ocean by the westernmost extension of Coney Island and the town of New Utrecht. The grant to Lady Moody and her supporters consisted of present-day Coney Island and all of Gravesend and Sheepshead Bay. Author Jacob Judd noted that Gravesend "was organized under a Dutch patent providing for freedom of worship and self-government and by the 1650s had become a well-known haven for persecuted Quakers." It was also the first grant of land in the New World to a female.
Sources:
Hicks, Saretta G. Dangerous Woman: A Biography of Deborah, Lady Moody of Coney Island. Unpublished manuscript.
Judd, Jacob. "Moody, [née Dunch], Deborah, Lady." The Encyclopedia of New York City. Ed. Kenneth T. Jackson. New Haven: Yale University Press and the New-York Historical Society, 1995: p. 767.
Related Materials
Town of Gravesend record transcriptions (1977.308)
Gravesend history collection (1978.046)
American Indians and English settlers Gravesend deed (1977.594)
William Henry Stillwell manuscript on the history of Gravesend (1977.309)
Transcriptions of Dutch legal documents on Flatbush, Flatlands, and Gravesend (1978.034)
Scope and Contents
In addition to materials pertaining to Lady Moody's life, this collection also contains correspondence. Most of this relates to Hicks's research during the period 1963 to 1965. A few letters, however, provide some insight into the author's personal life. Of particular note is a copy of the Hicks family's Christmas letter of 1964, written by Saretta Hicks and containing photographs of each of her family members. It provides a brief glimpse into Hicks's life as she balanced the demands of family and authorship. Another letter, written in 1965 to Ms. Mary Tatchell in England, sheds some light on why the book was never finished. This letter notes that she had two chapters ready to be sent to a publisher in hopes of obtaining a contract when she discovered some additional information that led her to question Lady Moody's date and place of birth. It appears that she decided to hold her manuscript until she could resolve the discrepancy. The exact dates of Lady Moody's birth and death still remain uncertain in current scholarship, as evidenced by her entry in The Encyclopedia of New York City, which gives her date of birth as "1583?" and her death as "between November 1658 and May 1659."
The collection is comprised of two accessions, 1978.170 and 1980.003. Material that comprises accession number 1978.170 consists of Ms. Hicks' correspondence and research notes. There are some magazine and newspaper clippings, as well as guidebooks to and photographs of sites in England. The photographs were at one time separated and assigned the number V1997.001. This portion of the collection also includes one book, English Historic Costume Painting Book: Elizabeth and James I, 1558-1625, No. 6 (London: Winsor & Newton, Ltd., 1947). Also included are copies of original documents about Lady Moody and her family, genealogical charts (pedigrees) tracing the lineage of the Moody family, and a genealogical chart for the Hicks family. Also included are a typed transcript of the 1645 patent for Gravesend and a four-page typed transcript of the Gravesend town meeting records of 1656.
Accession number 1980.003 consists of Hicks' typewritten manuscript of the first three chapters of "Dangerous Woman: A Biography of Deborah, Lady Moody of Coney Island" and outlines of the remaining chapters. The collection also contains newspaper and magazine clippings about various locations in Massachusetts, New York, and England, as well as four indexes. The first of these organizes information about significant people and events in Lady Moody's life. The second indexes major dates in the history of the Moody family. The third index presents information on Gravesend and includes a list of early settlers. The fourth indexes bibliographic sources.
Source:
Judd, Jacob. "Moody, [née Dunch], Deborah, Lady." The Encyclopedia of New York City. Ed. Kenneth T. Jackson. New Haven: Yale University Press and the New-York Historical Society, 1995: p. 767.
Research notes; Photographs; Correspondence; England; Gravesend (New York, N.Y.); Genealogies; Genealogy; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; Hicks, Saretta G.; Moody, Deborah, Lady
- Series 1: Research subject files, circa 1960s
  - Avebury (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Related Materials
    See also Series 4: Photographs.
    Scope and Contents
    Includes typed transcripts of depositions from 1598.
  - Bibliographies (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - England - research on life in 1600 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - England - travel journal, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Garsdon (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Gravesend (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Notes, clippings, copies, transcript of 1645 patent, transcript of 1656 town meeting records.
  - Huntingdon (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Indians (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Inns of Court (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Includes typed list of admissions to Lincoln's Inn for 1581-1619.
  - Kieft, William (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Little and Long Wittenham (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Includes typed transcript of translation of 1590s-1620s memorials to the Dunch family in the chapel at Little Wittenham.
  - London (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Lovelace, Henry (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Notes, guidebook, unidentified sketch bearing measurements.
  - Moody and Dunch families (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes copies of 16th-18th century originals.
  - Mervyn, Dunch, Stone and Moody families wills and funeral certificates (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Moody, Deborah (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Includes English Historic Costume Painting Book.
  - New Haven (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - New Netherlands (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Oxford and Cambridge (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Contains copies of original 1620s documents pertaining to Henry Moody.
  - Pedigrees (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Includes reproduction of circa 1670-1719 portrait of Edmund Dunch.
  - Pilkington family (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Rhode Island (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - St. Mary Aldermary church, London (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Includes typed transcript of church register, 1558-1611.
  - Thames river (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Wiltshire map and index (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Map depicts 1630.
- Series 2: Research indices, circa 1960s
  - Index to bibliographic sources (Box 3)
  - Index to people and events in Lady Deborah Moody's life (Box 4)
  - Index to dates in Moody family history (Box 4)
  - Index to Gravesend (Box 4)
- Series 3: Book manuscript, circa 1960s
  - Story ideas (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Preface and prologue (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Chapters 1-3 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Outlines of chapters 4-16 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Series 4: Photographs, circa 1960s; V1997.001 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  Includes photographs taken by Hicks of Avebury, Cambridge, Garsdon church, Henley, Huntingdon, Malmesbury, Little and Long Wittenham, London (including St. Mary Aldermary church), and Oxford in England, as well as Salem, Massachusetts.